<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Artur L Gower | Art L Gower</title>
    <link>https://arturgower.github.io/authors/artur-l-gower/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://arturgower.github.io/authors/artur-l-gower/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Artur L Gower</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2025 Artur L Gower</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 17:43:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://arturgower.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Artur L Gower</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/authors/artur-l-gower/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A model to validate effective waves in random particulate media: spherical symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/radial-effective/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/radial-effective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring the in-plane mechanical stress in a taut membrane is challenging, especially if its material parameters are unknown or altered by the stress. Yet being able to measure the stress is of fundamental interest to basic research and practical applications that use soft membranes, from engineering to tissues. Here, we present a robust non-destructive technique to measure directly in-situ stress and strain in soft thin films without the need to calibrate material parameters. Our method relies on measuring the speed of elastic waves propagating in the film. Using optical coherence tomography, we verify our method experimentally for a stretched rubber membrane, a piece of cling film (about 10 μm thick), and the leather skin of a traditional Irish frame drum. We find that our stress predictions are highly accurate and anticipate that our technique could be useful in applications ranging from soft matter devices to biomaterial engineering and medical diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noninvasive measurement of local stress inside soft materials with programmed shear waves</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/ultrasound-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2023 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/ultrasound-stress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mechanical stresses across different length scales play a fundamental role in understanding biological systems&amp;rsquo; functions and engineering soft machines and devices. However, it is challenging to noninvasively probe local mechanical stresses in situ, particularly when the mechanical properties are unknown. We propose an acoustoelastic imaging-based method to infer the local stresses in soft materials by measuring the speeds of shear waves induced by custom-programmed acoustic radiation force. Using an ultrasound transducer to excite and track the shear waves remotely, we demonstrate the application of the method by imaging uniaxial and bending stresses in an isotropic hydrogel and the passive uniaxial stress in a skeletal muscle. These measurements were all done without the knowledge of the constitutive parameters of the materials. The experiments indicate that our method will find broad applications, ranging from health monitoring of soft structures and machines to diagnosing diseases that alter stresses in soft tissues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A unified framework for linear thermo-visco-elastic wave propagation including the effects of stress-relaxation</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/thermo-visco-elastic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/thermo-visco-elastic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We present a unified framework for the study of wave propagation in homogeneous linear thermo-visco-elastic (TVE) continua, starting from conservation laws. In free-space such media admit two thermo-compressional modes and a shear mode. We provide asymptotic approximations to the corresponding wavenumbers which facilitate the understanding of dispersion of these modes, and consider common solids and fluids as well as soft materials where creep compliance and stress relaxation are important. We further illustrate how commonly used simpler acoustic/elastic dissipative theories can be derived via particular limits of this framework. Consequently, our framework allows us to: (i) simultaneously model interfaces involving both fluids and solids and (ii) easily quantify the influence of thermal or viscous losses in a given configuration of interest. As an example, the general framework is appliedto the canonical problem of scattering from an interface between two TVE half spaces in perfect contact. To illustrate, we provide results for fluid–solid interfaces involving air, water, steel and rubber, paying particular attention to the effects of stress relaxation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-destructive mapping of stress and strain in soft thin films through sound waves</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/thin-stress-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/thin-stress-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring the in-plane mechanical stress in a taut membrane is challenging, especially if its material parameters are unknown or altered by the stress. Yet being able to measure the stress is of fundamental interest to basic research and practical applications that use soft membranes, from engineering to tissues. Here, we present a robust non-destructive technique to measure directly in-situ stress and strain in soft thin films without the need to calibrate material parameters. Our method relies on measuring the speed of elastic waves propagating in the film. Using optical coherence tomography, we verify our method experimentally for a stretched rubber membrane, a piece of cling film (about 10 μm thick), and the leather skin of a traditional Irish frame drum. We find that our stress predictions are highly accurate and anticipate that our technique could be useful in applications ranging from soft matter devices to biomaterial engineering and medical diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An ultrasonic method to measure stress without calibration: The angled shear wave method</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/angled-ultrasonic-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/angled-ultrasonic-stress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring stress levels in loaded structures is crucial to assess and monitor structure health and to predict the length of remaining structural life. Many ultrasonic methods are able to accurately predict in-plane stresses inside a controlled laboratory environment but struggle to be robust outside, in a real-world setting. That is because these methods rely either on knowing beforehand the material constants (which are difficult to acquire) or require significant calibration for each specimen. This paper presents an ultrasonic method to evaluate the in-plane stress in situ directly, without knowing any material constants. The method is simple in principle, as it only requires measuring the speed of two angled shear waves. It is based on a formula that is exact for incompressible solids, such as soft gels or tissues, and is approximately true for compressible hard solids, such as steel and other metals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An ultrasonic method to measure stress without calibration: The angled shear wave method</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/angled-ultrasonic-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/angled-ultrasonic-stress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring stress levels in loaded structures is crucial to assess and monitor structure health and to predict the length of remaining structural life. Many ultrasonic methods are able to accurately predict in-plane stresses inside a controlled laboratory environment but struggle to be robust outside, in a real-world setting. That is because these methods rely either on knowing beforehand the material constants (which are difficult to acquire) or require significant calibration for each specimen. This paper presents an ultrasonic method to evaluate the in-plane stress in situ directly, without knowing any material constants. The method is simple in principle, as it only requires measuring the speed of two angled shear waves. It is based on a formula that is exact for incompressible solids, such as soft gels or tissues, and is approximately true for compressible hard solids, such as steel and other metals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Work With Me</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/post/work-with-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2019 13:58:32 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/post/work-with-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Am always happy to discuss research and exchange ideas. Find my &lt;a href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/#contact&#34;&gt;contact details here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- See below for funded PhD opportunities. --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;phd-positions&#34;&gt;PhD positions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like physics, maths, and programming, and want to work on exciting engineering and physics challenges, then please get in touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are currently three available funded PhD positions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../../pdf/PhDStudentshipInWaveScattering.pdf&#34;&gt;Sensing particles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../../pdf/UltrasonicWavesPhDFunding.pdf&#34;&gt;Waves or solid mechanics PhD position&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../../pdf/phd-fluids-sheffield.pdf&#34;&gt;Fluid mechanics PhD position&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- [click here to apply](https://www.sheffield.ac.uk/mecheng/phd/applying), but  --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am happy to discuss other potential PhD projects within the themes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/post/work-with-me/#modelling&#34;&gt;Modelling Waves in Complex Materials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/post/work-with-me/#particulates&#34;&gt;Wave Scattering from Particulates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/post/work-with-me/#elastic-waves&#34;&gt;Elastic wave propagation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;modelling&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;modelling-waves-in-complex-materials&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/project/complex-materials/&#34;&gt;Modelling Waves in Complex Materials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thousands of years ago, early Mesopotamian people discovered that a mixture of mud and straw creates strong durable buildings, what we call today a composite material. Today composite materials, and similarly complex fluids, have enabled amazing advances in areas including: aerospace, automobile, food science, communications technology, biotechnology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project focuses on waves (like sound, radio, light, and vibrations) interacting with these complex materials. Developing mathematical models of this interaction has two exciting goals: design the next generation of materials to &lt;strong&gt;control waves&lt;/strong&gt;, and use waves to &lt;strong&gt;sense and monitor complex material&lt;/strong&gt;. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/project/complex-materials/&#34;&gt;Waves in Complex Materials&lt;/a&gt; for more details.








  
  


&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
  

  
  
  
  
  
    
      
    
  
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-1&#34; data-caption=&#34;An emulsion made of oil particles in water. Makes up a large part of our food and oil industries.&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/emulsion.jpg&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/emulsion.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
  
  
  
    
      
    
  
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-1&#34; data-caption=&#34;A porous material, in this case the particles are pockets of air.&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/porous.jpg&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/porous.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
  
  
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Main skills:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classical mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Signal processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multivariable calculus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mathematical modelling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;particulates&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;wave-scattering-from-particulates&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../project/software-packages/&#34;&gt;Wave Scattering from Particulates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under close inspection, many natural and synthetic materials are composed of small randomly distributed particles. This is why
techniques to measure and predict these particle properties are important in many areas of science and engineering. Waves, either mechanical (like sound) or electromagnetic, are an excellent choice to probe particles because they can be non-invasive and energy efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project focuses on using, and developing, simulations of waves (like sound, radio, light, and vibrations) in particulate materials. The main goal is gain &lt;strong&gt;insight into the physics&lt;/strong&gt; and validate &lt;strong&gt;theoretical models&lt;/strong&gt;, though these simulations are very flexible, see &lt;a href=&#34;../../project/software-packages/&#34;&gt;Wave Software&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/project/complex-materials/&#34;&gt;Waves in Complex Materials&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/backscatter_time2.gif&#34; data-caption=&#34;Harmonic wave reflected from a random arrangement of particles.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/backscatter_time2.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Harmonic wave reflected from a random arrangement of particles.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Main skills:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Computer programming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Signal processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classical mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mathematical modelling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;elastic-waves&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;elastic-wave-propagation&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../project/ultrasonics/&#34;&gt;Elastic wave propagation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have built a world primarily out of steel, concrete, and other stiff solids. How well these structures endure depends on the tension and strains they are under, which are closely related to the material&amp;rsquo;s elastic behaviour. This is why elastic waves, such as vibrations, are an ideal choice to test the stress and strength of materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Projects in this theme will focus modelling and predicting a range of elastic waves (shear, surface, and compressional) in solids, such as steel under stress. For more details see &lt;a href=&#34;../../project/ultrasonics/&#34;&gt;Surface Waves&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/project/elasticity/&#34;&gt;Elastic materials under stress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/surface-wave.jpeg&#34; data-caption=&#34;An elastic wave propagating on the surface of a solid under tension.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/surface-wave.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    An elastic wave propagating on the surface of a solid under tension.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Main skills:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solid mechanics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mathematical modelling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wave motion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The constitutive relations of initially stressed incompressible Mooney-Rivlin materials</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/initial-mooney/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 15:02:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/initial-mooney/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/virtual.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Illustrates how the virtual stress-free state relates to a formulation purely in terms of stress tensors. B0 is virtual stress-free state, B1 is the initially stressed configuration with internal stress τ, and  B2 is the current configuration with Cauchy stress σ.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/virtual.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Illustrates how the virtual stress-free state relates to a formulation purely in terms of stress tensors. B0 is virtual stress-free state, B1 is the initially stressed configuration with internal stress τ, and  B2 is the current configuration with Cauchy stress σ.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Cable Positioning</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/industry/umbilical-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2016 20:25:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/industry/umbilical-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A subsea control umbilical is a collection of electrical, fibre optic cables, and fluid conduits bound together.  In offshore oil and gas field developments, umbilicals are critical so they need to be robust and flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is not limit to the number of possible designs that the cables can occupy, so it is not possible to just check them all. Instead, we need to allow, mathematically, these cables to be
placed any where as long as they do not overlap or break any other given restriction. Naturally this leads us to formulate the problem as an optimisation problem with continuous variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- 












&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/cables/OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif1.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/cables/OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;
 --&gt;
&lt;img style=&#34;width: 350px; float: right;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/cables/OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif1.png&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img style=&#34;width: 350px; float: right;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/cables/OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif4.png&#34;/&gt;
#### Figure 1:
 The light green cables are heavy steel cables, darker green are quad cables and the small purple one are fibre optical.  
&lt;img style=&#34;width: 350px; float: right;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/cables/OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif3.png&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img style=&#34;width: 350px; float: right;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/cables/OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif2.png&#34;/&gt;
#### Figure 2:
On the left we see a design which penalised steel cables touching (as it leads to greater wear and tear).
&lt;!--
\includegraphics[width=0.42\textwidth]{OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif1}
\includegraphics[width=0.42\textwidth]{OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif4}\\
$\mathbf{(1)}$ One layer and cost: 11.9 $C_{area}^{-1}$ \hspace{.2cm} $\mathbf{(2)}$ Two layer and cost: 12.9 $C_{area}^{-1}$
\includegraphics[width=0.42\textwidth]{OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif3}
\includegraphics[width=0.42\textwidth]{OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif2} \\
$\mathbf{(3)}$ Two layer and cost: 13.1 $C_{area}^{-1}$ \hspace{.2cm} $\mathbf{(4)}$ Two layer and cost: 13.1 $C_{area}^{-1}$
} --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Cable Positioning</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/industry/umbilical/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2016 20:25:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/industry/umbilical/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A subsea control umbilical is a collection of electrical, fibre optic cables, and fluid conduits bound together.  In offshore oil and gas field developments, umbilicals are critical so they need to be robust and flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is not limit to the number of possible designs that the cables can occupy, so it is not possible to just check them all. Instead, we need to allow, mathematically, these cables to be
placed any where as long as they do not overlap or break any other given restriction. Naturally this leads us to formulate the problem as an optimisation problem with continuous variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- 












&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/cables/OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif1.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/cables/OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;
 --&gt;
&lt;img style=&#34;width: 350px; float: right;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/cables/OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif1.png&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img style=&#34;width: 350px; float: right;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/cables/OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif4.png&#34;/&gt;
#### Figure 1:
 The light green cables are heavy steel cables, darker green are quad cables and the small purple one are fibre optical.  
&lt;img style=&#34;width: 350px; float: right;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/cables/OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif3.png&#34;/&gt;
&lt;img style=&#34;width: 350px; float: right;&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/cables/OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif2.png&#34;/&gt;
#### Figure 2:
On the left we see a design which penalised steel cables touching (as it leads to greater wear and tear).
&lt;!--
\includegraphics[width=0.42\textwidth]{OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif1}
\includegraphics[width=0.42\textwidth]{OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif4}\\
$\mathbf{(1)}$ One layer and cost: 11.9 $C_{area}^{-1}$ \hspace{.2cm} $\mathbf{(2)}$ Two layer and cost: 12.9 $C_{area}^{-1}$
\includegraphics[width=0.42\textwidth]{OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif3}
\includegraphics[width=0.42\textwidth]{OptimalCables2Are=Ste=4Stif2} \\
$\mathbf{(3)}$ Two layer and cost: 13.1 $C_{area}^{-1}$ \hspace{.2cm} $\mathbf{(4)}$ Two layer and cost: 13.1 $C_{area}^{-1}$
} --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elimination of errors from track line detection, In: Train Positioning Using Video Odometry</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/industry/train/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2014 20:40:02 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/industry/train/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/train.gif&#34; data-caption=&#34;Estimated track in red compared with the camera image in blue. As the train shakes, so does the camera.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/train.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Estimated track in red compared with the camera image in blue. As the train shakes, so does the camera.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!-- width=&#34;220&#34; --&gt;
  &lt;!-- &lt;img style=&#34;width: 400px; float: right;&#34; alt=&#34;Track reconstruction&#34; src=&#34;train.gif&#34; hspace=&#34;2&#34; /&gt; --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	To increase the number of trains running on each track we have to be able to accurately locate every train, at each moment. GPS can be unreliable because of the multitude of tunnels, so we looked at using a camera mounted on top of the train pointed down at the tracks. From the image of this camera an on-board computer can locate the train&#39;s location.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	At least that is the theory. One major difficulty is that the train shakes unpredictably, which the camera sees as the track moving and changing shape unpredictably. To eliminate these errors we formulated an optimisation method for each frame. This method attempts to separate the errors due to shaking from the tracks real curvature. On the right is the result of the method taking what &lt;span style=&#34;color: blue;&#34;&gt;the camera sees&lt;/span&gt;, the blue tracks, and returning the &lt;span style=&#34;color: red;&#34;&gt;real position of the tracks&lt;/span&gt;, in red.  
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figures below show how well our method &lt;span style=&#34;color: black;&#34;&gt;recovers&lt;/span&gt; the track curvature compared with the  &lt;span style=&#34;color: green;&#34;&gt;real curvature&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 &lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/alpha_error.png&#34;&gt;
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 &lt;figure&gt;
 
 
   &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/beta_error.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Above we see the estimated planar curvature $\alpha$ and vertical curvature $\beta$, both in black, compared to the real curvatures $\alpha^* $ and $\beta^* $ in green.&#34;&gt;
 &lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/beta_error.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
 
 
   
   
   &lt;figcaption&gt;
     Above we see the estimated planar curvature $\alpha$ and vertical curvature $\beta$, both in black, compared to the real curvatures $\alpha^* $ and $\beta^* $ in green.
   &lt;/figcaption&gt;
 
 
 &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;!--
On the right we see the estimated planar curvature &amp;alpha; and vertical curvature &amp;beta;, both in black, compared to the &lt;span style=&#34;color: green;&#34;&gt; real curvatures&lt;/span&gt; in green.
--&gt;
  &lt;!-- &lt;img style=&#34;width: 350px;  float: right;&#34; alt=&#34;Curvature errors&#34; src=&#34;Pictures/alpha_error.jpg&#34; hspace=&#34;2&#34; /&gt;
	&lt;img style=&#34;width: 350px;  float: right;&#34; alt=&#34;Curvature errors&#34; src=&#34;Pictures/beta_error.jpg&#34; hspace=&#34;2&#34; /&gt; --&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
