<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2 | Art L Gower</title>
    <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication_types/2/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://arturgower.github.io/publication_types/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>2</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2025 Artur L Gower</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 17:43:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://arturgower.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>2</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication_types/2/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A model to validate effective waves in random particulate media: spherical symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/radial-effective/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/radial-effective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring the in-plane mechanical stress in a taut membrane is challenging, especially if its material parameters are unknown or altered by the stress. Yet being able to measure the stress is of fundamental interest to basic research and practical applications that use soft membranes, from engineering to tissues. Here, we present a robust non-destructive technique to measure directly in-situ stress and strain in soft thin films without the need to calibrate material parameters. Our method relies on measuring the speed of elastic waves propagating in the film. Using optical coherence tomography, we verify our method experimentally for a stretched rubber membrane, a piece of cling film (about 10 μm thick), and the leather skin of a traditional Irish frame drum. We find that our stress predictions are highly accurate and anticipate that our technique could be useful in applications ranging from soft matter devices to biomaterial engineering and medical diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noninvasive measurement of local stress inside soft materials with programmed shear waves</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/ultrasound-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2023 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/ultrasound-stress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mechanical stresses across different length scales play a fundamental role in understanding biological systems&amp;rsquo; functions and engineering soft machines and devices. However, it is challenging to noninvasively probe local mechanical stresses in situ, particularly when the mechanical properties are unknown. We propose an acoustoelastic imaging-based method to infer the local stresses in soft materials by measuring the speeds of shear waves induced by custom-programmed acoustic radiation force. Using an ultrasound transducer to excite and track the shear waves remotely, we demonstrate the application of the method by imaging uniaxial and bending stresses in an isotropic hydrogel and the passive uniaxial stress in a skeletal muscle. These measurements were all done without the knowledge of the constitutive parameters of the materials. The experiments indicate that our method will find broad applications, ranging from health monitoring of soft structures and machines to diagnosing diseases that alter stresses in soft tissues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Representing the stress and strain energy of elastic solids with initial stress and transverse texture anisotropy</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/anisotropic-initial-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 19:23:19 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/anisotropic-initial-stress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Real-world solids, such as rocks, soft tissues and engineering materials, are often under some form of stress. Most real materials are also, to some degree, anisotropic due to their microstructure, a characteristic often called the ‘texture anisotropy’. This anisotropy can stem from preferential grain alignment in polycrystalline materials, aligned micro-cracks or structural reinforcement, such as collagen bundles in biological tissues, steel rods in pre-stressed concrete and reinforcing fibres in composites. Here, we establish a framework for initially stressed solids with transverse texture anisotropy. We consider that the strain energy per unit mass of the reference is an explicit function of the elastic deformation gradient, the initial stress tensor and the texture anisotropy. We determine the corresponding constitutive relations and develop examples of nonlinear strain energies that depend explicitly on the initial stress and direction of texture anisotropy. As an application, we then employ these models to analyse the stress distribution of an inflated initially stressed cylinder with texture anisotropy and the tension of a welded metal plate. We also deduce the elastic moduli needed to describe linear elasticity from stress reference with transverse texture anisotropy. As an example, we show how to measure the stress with small-amplitude shear waves.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A unified framework for linear thermo-visco-elastic wave propagation including the effects of stress-relaxation</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/thermo-visco-elastic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/thermo-visco-elastic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We present a unified framework for the study of wave propagation in homogeneous linear thermo-visco-elastic (TVE) continua, starting from conservation laws. In free-space such media admit two thermo-compressional modes and a shear mode. We provide asymptotic approximations to the corresponding wavenumbers which facilitate the understanding of dispersion of these modes, and consider common solids and fluids as well as soft materials where creep compliance and stress relaxation are important. We further illustrate how commonly used simpler acoustic/elastic dissipative theories can be derived via particular limits of this framework. Consequently, our framework allows us to: (i) simultaneously model interfaces involving both fluids and solids and (ii) easily quantify the influence of thermal or viscous losses in a given configuration of interest. As an example, the general framework is appliedto the canonical problem of scattering from an interface between two TVE half spaces in perfect contact. To illustrate, we provide results for fluid–solid interfaces involving air, water, steel and rubber, paying particular attention to the effects of stress relaxation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-destructive mapping of stress and strain in soft thin films through sound waves</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/thin-stress-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/thin-stress-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring the in-plane mechanical stress in a taut membrane is challenging, especially if its material parameters are unknown or altered by the stress. Yet being able to measure the stress is of fundamental interest to basic research and practical applications that use soft membranes, from engineering to tissues. Here, we present a robust non-destructive technique to measure directly in-situ stress and strain in soft thin films without the need to calibrate material parameters. Our method relies on measuring the speed of elastic waves propagating in the film. Using optical coherence tomography, we verify our method experimentally for a stretched rubber membrane, a piece of cling film (about 10 μm thick), and the leather skin of a traditional Irish frame drum. We find that our stress predictions are highly accurate and anticipate that our technique could be useful in applications ranging from soft matter devices to biomaterial engineering and medical diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effective waves for random three-dimensional particulate materials</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/effective-waves-3d/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 18:03:04 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/effective-waves-3d/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;How do you take a reliable measurement of a material whose microstructure is random? When using wave scattering, the answer is often to take an ensemble average (average over time or space). By ensemble averaging we can calculate the average scattered wave and the effective wavenumber. To date, the literature has focused on calculating the effective wavenumber for a plate filled with particles. One clear unanswered question was how to extend this approach to a material of any geometry and for any source. For example, does the effective wavenumber depend on only the microstructure, or also on the material geometry? In this work, we demonstrate that the effective wavenumbers depend on only microstructure, though beyond the long wavelength limit there are multiple effective wavenumbers for one fixed incident frequency. We show how to calculate the average wave scattered from a random particulate material of any shape, and for broad frequency ranges. As an example, we show how to calculate the average wave scattered from a sphere filled with particles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/eff-sphere-scatter.gif&#34; data-caption=&#34;Shows the average scattering of a harmonic wave according to the effective waves theory.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/eff-sphere-scatter.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Shows the average scattering of a harmonic wave according to the effective waves theory.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An ultrasonic method to measure stress without calibration: The angled shear wave method</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/angled-ultrasonic-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/angled-ultrasonic-stress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring stress levels in loaded structures is crucial to assess and monitor structure health and to predict the length of remaining structural life. Many ultrasonic methods are able to accurately predict in-plane stresses inside a controlled laboratory environment but struggle to be robust outside, in a real-world setting. That is because these methods rely either on knowing beforehand the material constants (which are difficult to acquire) or require significant calibration for each specimen. This paper presents an ultrasonic method to evaluate the in-plane stress in situ directly, without knowing any material constants. The method is simple in principle, as it only requires measuring the speed of two angled shear waves. It is based on a formula that is exact for incompressible solids, such as soft gels or tissues, and is approximately true for compressible hard solids, such as steel and other metals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An ultrasonic method to measure stress without calibration: The angled shear wave method</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/angled-ultrasonic-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/angled-ultrasonic-stress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Measuring stress levels in loaded structures is crucial to assess and monitor structure health and to predict the length of remaining structural life. Many ultrasonic methods are able to accurately predict in-plane stresses inside a controlled laboratory environment but struggle to be robust outside, in a real-world setting. That is because these methods rely either on knowing beforehand the material constants (which are difficult to acquire) or require significant calibration for each specimen. This paper presents an ultrasonic method to evaluate the in-plane stress in situ directly, without knowing any material constants. The method is simple in principle, as it only requires measuring the speed of two angled shear waves. It is based on a formula that is exact for incompressible solids, such as soft gels or tissues, and is approximately true for compressible hard solids, such as steel and other metals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Proof that Multiple Waves Propagate in Ensemble-Averaged Particulate Materials</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/prove-multiple-waves/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2019 11:29:37 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/prove-multiple-waves/</guid>
      <description>












&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/multiple-waves-diagram.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Caption: When an incident plane wave $\mathrm e^{i \mathbf k \cdot (x,y)}$ with $\mathbf k = k(\cos \theta, \sin \theta)$, encounters an (ensemble-averaged) particulate material, it excites many transmitted plane waves and one reflected plane wave. The transmitted waves are of the form $\mathrm e^{i \mathbf s_p \cdot (x,y)}$ with wavenumbers $\mathbf s_p = S_p (\cos \theta_p, \sin \theta_p)$ (details in paper) where both $S_p$ and $\theta_p$ are complex numbers. The larger Im $\mathbf s_p$, the more quickly the wave attenuates as it propagates into the half-space and the smaller the drawn vector for that wave above.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/multiple-waves-diagram.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Caption: When an incident plane wave $\mathrm e^{i \mathbf k \cdot (x,y)}$ with $\mathbf k = k(\cos \theta, \sin \theta)$, encounters an (ensemble-averaged) particulate material, it excites many transmitted plane waves and one reflected plane wave. The transmitted waves are of the form $\mathrm e^{i \mathbf s_p \cdot (x,y)}$ with wavenumbers $\mathbf s_p = S_p (\cos \theta_p, \sin \theta_p)$ (details in paper) where both $S_p$ and $\theta_p$ are complex numbers. The larger Im $\mathbf s_p$, the more quickly the wave attenuates as it propagates into the half-space and the smaller the drawn vector for that wave above.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/ComplexKernel.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;These are the kind of complex phase plot you need to deal with to use the Wiener-Hopf method.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/ComplexKernel.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    These are the kind of complex phase plot you need to deal with to use the Wiener-Hopf method.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Waves Propagate in Random Particulate Materials</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/multiple-waves/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 11:59:32 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/multiple-waves/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/average_scat_harmonic.gif&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/average_scat_harmonic.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the right of the dashed line are particles, whose position has been numerically ensemble averaged. To the left is just a homogenious medium. What is shown here (though faintly) is that more than one transmitted wave exists in an ensemble averaged medium. The paper shows this with much more clarity!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characterising particulate random media from near-surface backscattering: A machine learning approach to predict particle size and concentration</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/learning_backscattering/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2018 20:08:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/learning_backscattering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/backscatter.jpg&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/backscatter.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflection from a multi-species material and its transmitted effective wavenumber</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/multi-species/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2018 19:53:40 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/multi-species/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/multispecies.jpg&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/multispecies.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!--
Justification Statement: the originality, significance and rigour of this output (up to 100 words).
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particulate materials (emulsions, powders, blood) have led to significant advances in foods science and healthcare. To automate the production of these materials or to monitor them in use, waves such as acoustics and light are essential. One open challenge has been to describe waves in particles with different sizes and properties (multi-species). These variations in particle properties are key indicators of performance. This paper is the first to derive a rigorous model, and demonstrates the deficiencies of current ad hoc models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Factual information about the significance of the output --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quoting the British Standards (ISO 20998-3:2017): &amp;ldquo;Ultrasonic spectroscopy is widely used to measure particle size distribution (PSD) in colloids, dispersions, and emulsions&amp;rdquo;. Yet, despite the widespread use and importance of these methods, the ISO publication describes that there does not exist a rigorous model for acoustics in polydisperse particles (multi-species). This paper clearly fills this gap in the knowledge, and provides simply accessible formulas, as well a software package (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/arturgower/EffectiveWaves.jl&#34;&gt;https://github.com/arturgower/EffectiveWaves.jl&lt;/a&gt;) for a vast range of different particle materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--
Reviewers:
- This extension to the multi-species case is non-trivial and leads to some counter-intuitive results.
- This paper ... makes original and worthwhile extensions of knowledge.
--&gt;
&lt;!-- For co-authored or co-produced outputs, details of the contribution of the individual submitted researcher

Artur Gower drafted the manuscript, derived the mathematical expressions, and carried out all the numerical calculations. The other authors made contributions to the text, and helped conceive the study.

--&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The constitutive relations of initially stressed incompressible Mooney-Rivlin materials</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/initial-mooney/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 15:02:35 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/initial-mooney/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/virtual.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Illustrates how the virtual stress-free state relates to a formulation purely in terms of stress tensors. B0 is virtual stress-free state, B1 is the initially stressed configuration with internal stress τ, and  B2 is the current configuration with Cauchy stress σ.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/virtual.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Illustrates how the virtual stress-free state relates to a formulation purely in terms of stress tensors. B0 is virtual stress-free state, B1 is the initially stressed configuration with internal stress τ, and  B2 is the current configuration with Cauchy stress σ.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new restriction for initially stressed elastic solids</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/stress-objectivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2017 10:23:51 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/stress-objectivity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/uniaxial.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;This is from an example that illustrates that even uniaxial deformations lead to unphysical results, if our restriction is not satisfied.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/uniaxial.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    This is from an example that illustrates that even uniaxial deformations lead to unphysical results, if our restriction is not satisfied.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oblique Wrinkles</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/oblique-wrinkles/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2017 14:41:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/oblique-wrinkles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/FiberBucklingSolution.jpeg&#34; data-caption=&#34;The wrinkles do not always align in the direction of greatest stress or aligned with the fibres.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/FiberBucklingSolution.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The wrinkles do not always align in the direction of greatest stress or aligned with the fibres.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!--
Justification Statement: the originality, significance and rigour of this output (up to 100 words).
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soft solids, such as silicon, rubber, soft tissues, can undergo large strains and compression. During compression, a wrinkle can form on the material&amp;rsquo;s surface. These wrinkles are used to, for example: create microlens arrays, tune surface wetting and adhesion. Alternatively, they can be undesirable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guided by physical intuition, it was thought that wrinkles always form orthogonal to the direction of greatest compression. In this paper, we demonstrate that wrinkles at different angles (oblique) can supersede all other wrinkles, according to the theory of nonlinear elasticity. This affects both how early wrinkles form and their pattern. However, our table top experiments with gelatin do not confirm these findings. We go to show that a non-oblique creases may supersede our oblique wrinkles. Till today, the competition between creases and wrinkles is still an unresolved issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Factual information about the significance of the output

This oblique wrinkle work led to this paper and to an Irish Research Council Postgraduate Scholarship (GOIPG/2013/260) - 46k euro.

How wrinkles form underpins many techniques across science and engineering, see examples below. All these methods rely on an intuitive assumption: that wrinkles form orthogonal to the directions of greatest tension. Our work demonstrates that rigours theory does not confirm this assumption.

 Examples include:
- use surface wrinkles to tune surface wetting and adhesion.
- to pattern microlens array (used in fibre optics and optical computing), to create wavy stretchable electronics which can undergo large strains without breaking.   
- avoiding wrinkling in flexible displays and eletro-textiles.  

Reviewers quotes:
- I learned a number of new things from this paper ... The occurrence of wrinkles
that are aligned obliquely as revealed by the authors was unexpected to me.
- A very original paper, clearly written and containing pertinent informations.

--&gt;
&lt;!-- For co-authored or co-produced outputs, details of the contribution of the individual submitted researcher

Artur Gower developed much of the mathematical framework, constitutive models, and linear stability analysis, and the graphs resulting from these. All authors helped draft the manuscript, and P.C conceived of the study.

--&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphology of residually stressed tubular tissues: Beyond the elastic multiplicative decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/tube-morphology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2016 15:10:20 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/tube-morphology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/tube-table.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Illustrates the kind of wrinkling instabilities that appear for different distributions of residual stress. These studies can help explain the morphology of tubular structures. For a growing tissue, like our intestine, to form a specific type of wrinkle, it need only generate the right kind of stress, then the tube will spontaneously wrinkle.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/tube-table.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Illustrates the kind of wrinkling instabilities that appear for different distributions of residual stress. These studies can help explain the morphology of tubular structures. For a growing tissue, like our intestine, to form a specific type of wrinkle, it need only generate the right kind of stress, then the tube will spontaneously wrinkle.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!--
Justification Statement: the originality, significance and rigour of this output (up to 100 words).
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mammal physiology has an incredible range of patterns, from the folded structure of brains, to the wrinkles along intestines. How do these patterns emerge, and what do they tell us about the mechanics of these tissues? These patterns often result from mechanical instabilities, and previous studies were able to predict a variety of patterns from simple scenarios, such as increasing pressure in a tube. However, these previous studies needed to make use of an abstract construct, a virtual state that the material never occupies. In this paper, we our the first to show that a large variety of tissue patterns can be predicted by simply altering the internal stresses. This clear connection between internal stresses and patterning allows us to clearly connect the tissue&amp;rsquo;s mechanical function and properties to its pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Factual information about the significance of the output

This paper was the first to demonstrate how internals stress can be directly related to pattern formation (through instabilities). A range of papers on pattern formation in soft tissues have resulted from this work, including:
- patterns formation on elastic spheres (like the early stage of an embryo) due to internal stresses.
- wrinkles forming on stressed thin films (used in flexible electronics and surface patterning).
- pattern formation on layered aorta (a large artery).
- theoretical frameworks which connect tissue growth, internal stress, with pattern formation.

--&gt;
&lt;!-- For co-authored or co-produced outputs, details of the contribution of the individual submitted researcher

Artur Gower developed much of the mathematical framework, constitutive models, and linear stability analysis, and the graphs resulting from these. All authors helped draft the manuscript, and P.C conceived of the study.

--&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On residual stresses and homeostasis: an elastic theory of functional adaptation in living matter</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/homeostasis-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2016 15:56:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/homeostasis-stress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/wapa.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Illustrates a Wapa tree that explodes when cut, because it is releasing a tremendous amount of residual stress.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/wapa.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Illustrates a Wapa tree that explodes when cut, because it is releasing a tremendous amount of residual stress.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Higher-order reverse automatic differentiation with emphasis on the third-order</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/third-order-ad/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2016 16:14:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/third-order-ad/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Initial stress symmetry and its applications in elasticity</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/stress-symmetry-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2015 21:04:51 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/stress-symmetry-2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!--
Justification Statement: the originality, significance and rigour of this output (up to 100 words).
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stresses in solids can arise due to an external load, or from internal changes such as thermal expansion and growth. Significant residual stress are present in biological tissues due to growth, in most metal due to cooling and rolling, and even in the earths crust due to gravity and active tectonics. These stresses greatly alter the elastic behaviour of a solid, which is the theme of this work. This paper demonstrated that a basic physical law (related to energy conservation) was missing from all the elastic models in the field. This physical law also allows elegant shortcuts to model in-vivo stress conditions, which we used to model the elastic behaviour of an artery under ideal in-vivo conditions. Previous studies needed to use heavy numerical implementations to achieve a similar non-optimal result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Factual information about the significance of the output --&gt;
&lt;!--

Anonymous reviewer:
So far [there does not exist] in the literature a general non-destructive method or theory to compute [initial stresses]. The present paper [helps achieve this goal and] will have many applications in the future.

So far this paper has directly led over 10 different studies and methods (mostly in the form of published papers).

Main impact: this work changed the communities approach to modelling elastic solids under stress. Before, it was thought that pre-stresses (like a residual stress) could easily be accounted for in the elastic behaviour. The new law introduced in this paper changed that view. Since publication, there have been far fewer papers explicitly modelling the nonlinear elastic behaviour of solids under stress. Papers that have been published have almost all exclusively used a model introduced in this paper, which is one of the few known to satisfy the extra physical law.




--&gt;
&lt;!-- For co-authored or co-produced outputs, details of the contribution of the individual submitted researcher

Artur Gower conceived of the study, developed the theoretical framework, and produced the numerical results and graphs.

--&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connecting the material parameters of soft fibre-reinforced solids with the formation of surface wrinkles</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/fibre-wrinkle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 19:21:07 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/fibre-wrinkle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we compress a soft solid enough, it will form wrinkles on its surface, as shown by the figure below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/Shearing.gif&#34; data-caption=&#34;When a soft solid is sheared enough, it will form wrinkles on its surface. The black lines show the directions of reinforcing fibres.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/Shearing.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    When a soft solid is sheared enough, it will form wrinkles on its surface. The black lines show the directions of reinforcing fibres.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most biological materials (and industrial) are reinforced with stiff fibres. Knowing how these wrinkles form&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;will give us greater control when creating textured surfaces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;helps us understand how wrinkled surfaces form in biology, like the lining of our gut.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;allow us to use these wrinkles to learn about the material and its fibres.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last item is the focus of this paper. I study carefully the link between all possible fibres and how they effect the formation of surface wrinkles. The figure below illustrates part of the mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/WrinkleMov.gif&#34; data-caption=&#34;At each stage of the deformation, we check is there exists a wrinkle which will minimise the potential energy of the material. If such a wrinkle does exists, we know that it will form instantly.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/WrinkleMov.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    At each stage of the deformation, we check is there exists a wrinkle which will minimise the potential energy of the material. If such a wrinkle does exists, we know that it will form instantly.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A robust anisotropic hyperelastic formulation for the modelling of soft tissue</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/robust-anisotropy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 16:34:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/robust-anisotropy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/stent-arteries.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Contour plots illustrating the stresses computed for the standard arterial wall model (HGO-C) and our modified model (MA) after stent deployment. A) von Mises stress q, B) pressure stress -σ hyd, C) triaxiality, D) ratio of axial stress to the circumferential stress σ_zz /σ_θθ.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/stent-arteries.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Contour plots illustrating the stresses computed for the standard arterial wall model (HGO-C) and our modified model (MA) after stent deployment. A) von Mises stress q, B) pressure stress -σ hyd, C) triaxiality, D) ratio of axial stress to the circumferential stress σ_zz /σ_θθ.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;!--
Justification Statement: the originality, significance and rigour of this output (up to 100 words).
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modelling soft tissues has an immense potential to impact healthcare. It will enable a revolution of simulated surgeries, and long term predictions of prosthetics in the human body. Most soft tissues are reinforced by fibres (anisotropic). In this paper, we demonstrated how to implement, in finite element, robust models of anisotropic soft tissues. We were the first to correctly model volumetric changes in soft tissues, which, previously, were ignored by most finite element methods. To demonstrate the importance of our method, we simulated a stent deployed in an artery, and showed how the arterial forces were significantly under predicted with previous models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Factual information about the significance of the output --&gt;
&lt;!-- This papers has influenced a wide community which models soft tissues with finite element.
 By tracking the 80+ citations of this paper, some of the numerous  
 Some
 contributions that our method led to include
- robust simulations of arteries walls in numerous papers including: studying passive and active behaviour, optimising stent deployment, modelling the mechanics of plaque formation, and models for vein reconstruction surgeries (from venous valve tissue).
- improved models of tendons and ligaments in knees and other joints, which help optimise surgical methods, and avoid tears.
- models of the elastic behaviour of skin tissues.
- mechano-electrochemical models for smooth muscle contraction.
--&gt;
&lt;!-- For co-authored or co-produced outputs, details of the contribution of the individual submitted researcher

Artur Gower developed both the theoretical framework, mathematical examples, and custom elasticity tensors used by Abacus (finite element software. David Nolan developed and implemented the simulations examples in the paper. All authors helped draft the manuscript and conceive the study.

--&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Counter-intuitive results in acousto-elasticity</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/acousto-elasticity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2013 19:51:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/acousto-elasticity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/surface-wave.jpeg&#34; data-caption=&#34;A plane surface wave travelling on the top of a deformed soft solid.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/surface-wave.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A plane surface wave travelling on the top of a deformed soft solid.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We revisit the theory of acousto-elasticity in deformed isotropic solids.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intuition suggests that slowest and the fastest waves should travel along the directions of least and greatest stretch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We find examples where this is not the case, for body and for surface waves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These results complicate accepted protocols for finding the directions of greatest strains.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shear instability in skin tissue</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/skin-shear/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 20:00:17 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/skin-shear/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/skin-shear.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;On the left the skin at rest, on the right we shear the skin until wrinkles form. What can these wrinkles tell us about the skin?&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/skin-shear.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;90%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    On the left the skin at rest, on the right we shear the skin until wrinkles form. What can these wrinkles tell us about the skin?
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We explore how the alignment of surface wrinkles relate to the directions of the reinforcing fibres in the skin. This technique is used to estimate the Langer lines (directions of greatest tension), which then indicates where incisions are best made for surgery.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
