<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Effective Waves | Art L Gower</title>
    <link>https://arturgower.github.io/tags/effective-waves/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://arturgower.github.io/tags/effective-waves/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Effective Waves</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2026 Artur L Gower</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 19:51:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://arturgower.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Effective Waves</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/tags/effective-waves/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acoustic waves in a halfspace material filled with random particulate</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/xqca/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 19:51:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/xqca/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Particulate materials include powders, emulsions, composites, and many others. This is why measuring these has become important for both industry and scientific applications. For industrial applications, the greatest need is to measure dense particulates, in-situ, and non-destructively. In theory, this could be achieved with acoustics: the standard method is to send an acoustic wave through the particulate and then attempt to measure the effective wave speed and attenuation. A major obstacle here is that it is not clear how to relate the effective wave speed and attenuation to the reflection and transmission coefficients, which are far easier to measure. This is because it has been very difficult to mathematically account for different background mediums. In this paper, we resolve this obstacle. To help comprehension, we present how to account for different background mediums for a simple case: a halfspace filled with a random particulate, where the background of the halfspace is different from the exterior medium. The key to solving this problem was to derive a systematic extension of a widely used closure approximation: the quasi-crystalline approximation. We present some numerical results to demonstrate that the reflection coefficient can be easily calculated for a broad range of frequencies and particle properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RMgwe3wfVgQ?si=YtZUbB_HHbrnc5m0&#34; title=&#34;YouTube video player&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allow=&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34; referrerpolicy=&#34;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effective T-matrix of a cylinder filled with a random two-dimensional particulate</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/effective-t-matrix/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2024 19:51:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/effective-t-matrix/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When a wave, such as sound or light, scatters within a densely packed particulate, it can be rescattered many times between the particles, which is called multiple scattering. Multiple scattering can be unavoidable when trying to use sound waves to measure a dense particulate, such as a composite with reinforcing fibres. Here, we solve from first principles multiple scattering of scalar waves, including acoustic, for any frequency from a set of two-dimensional particles confined in a circular area. This case has not been solved yet, and its solution is important to perform numerical validation, as particles within a cylinder require only a finite number of particles to perform direct numerical simulations. The method we use involves ensemble averaging over particle configurations, which leads us to deduce an effective T-matrix for the whole cylinder, which can be used to easily describe the scattering from any incident wave. In the specific case when the particles are monopole scatterers, the expression of this effective T-matrix simplifies and reduces to the T-matrix of a homogeneous cylinder with an effective wavenumber⁠. To validate our theoretical predictions, we develop an efficient Monte Carlo method and conclude that our theoretical predictions are highly accurate for a broad range of frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A model to validate effective waves in random particulate media: spherical symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/radial-effective/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Nov 2023 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/complex-materials/radial-effective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There has not been a satisfying numerical validation of the theory of effective waves in random particulate materials. Validation has been challenging because the theoretical methods for effective waves have been limited to random particulate media in infinite slabs or half-spaces, which require a very large number of particles to perform accurate numerical simulations. This paper offers a solution by providing, from first principles, a method to calculate effective waves for a sphere filled with particles for a spherically symmetric incident wave. We show that this case can excite exactly the same effective wavenumbers, which are the most important feature to validate for effective waves. To check correctness, we also deduce an integral equation method which does not assume the effective wave solution. Our methods are, in principal, valid for any frequency, particle volume fraction and disordered pair-correlation. With the methods we provide, it is now possible to validate, with a heavier Monte Carlo simulation, the predictions from effective wave theory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EffectiveWaves.jl</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/effective-wave-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2017 10:29:53 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/effective-wave-software/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The software is designed to calculate effective waves propagating, and scattering from, random materials filled with particles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/compare_concrete.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/compare_concrete.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Waves in Complex Materials</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/project/complex-materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/project/complex-materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;complex-materials&#34;&gt;Complex materials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thousands of years ago, early Mesopotamian people discovered that a mixture of mud and straw  creates strong durable buildings, what we call today a composite material. Composites are far better than the sum of their parts, for example they can be stronger and cheaper. Hundreds of years of experimentation has led to similar discoveries when mixing fluids and gases, what we now call complex fluids/media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today composite materials and complex fluids have enabled amazing advances in areas including: aerospace, automobile, food science, communications technology, biotechnology.&lt;/p&gt;








  
  


&lt;div class=&#34;gallery&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
  

  
  
  
  
  
    
      
    
  
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-1&#34; data-caption=&#34;A Nylon powder.&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/nylon-powder.jpg&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/nylon-powder.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
  
  
  
    
      
    
  
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-1&#34; data-caption=&#34;An emulsion made of oil particles in water.&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/emulsion.jpg&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/emulsion.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
  
  
  
    
      
    
  
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-1&#34; data-caption=&#34;An suspension of gases bubbles in air.&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/bubbles.jpg&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/bubbles.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
  
  
  
    
      
    
  
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-1&#34; data-caption=&#34;A porous material, in this case the particles are pockets of air.&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/porous.jpg&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/pics/porous.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  
  
  
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click on images above. Metal matrix foams and fibre composites are examples of composites, while emulsions, suspensions, complex gases, and polymers are complex fluids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My research focuses on waves (like sound, radio, light, and vibrations) interacting with these complex materials. Developing mathematical models of this interaction has two exciting goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Controlling waves&lt;/strong&gt; by designing the next generation of materials. These new materials can then improve telecommunications by controlling light and elastic waves, and mechanical engineering by controlling vibrations and even earthquakes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sensing materials&lt;/strong&gt; with waves. We sense the world around us by using waves. Light and sound are reflected from all materials, and when they reach us, our brains can decode them to understand what objects are around us. In a similar way, waves are used to sense the microstructure materials. One use is to automate manufacturing, where we need to develop sensors that can detect changes in microstructure from reflected waves. Keeping track of the microstructure is essential to determine when the material has reached its optimally flexibility, strength, or capacity to transmit information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;mathematical-models&#34;&gt;Mathematical models&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all these complex materials, it is impossible to know the exact position and shapes of all the microstructure. But the reflected wave does depend on the configuration of the microstructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;












&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/backscatter_complex.gif&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/backscatter_complex.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

Caption: one reflected wave from a complex material. What can we learn about this material from measuring the wave at the receiver?













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/moments.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/moments.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

Caption: the wave reflected from the same complex material can be different each time if its microstructure moves, or if the position of the receiver moves. For example the grey curves above are all different reflected waves from the same material. To make sense of these curves, we investigate the average (mean: black curve) reflected wave, and the variation of the reflected waves (std: green region).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Figures made with &lt;a href=&#34;../software-packages/&#34;&gt;wave scattering software&lt;/a&gt; I develop)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to develop mathematical models which predict the average reflected wave and its variance (or standard deviation), as these do not depend on the configuration of the microstructure. One of our discoveries [&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.10816&#34;&gt;paper 1&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.06996&#34;&gt;paper 2&lt;/a&gt;] is that there exists many waves, with different speeds and characteristics, that can propagate
(in an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ensemble_average_(statistical_mechanics)&#34;&gt;ensemble averaged&lt;/a&gt; sense) inside these complex materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have accurate mathematical models, and &lt;a href=&#34;../software-packages/&#34;&gt;software&lt;/a&gt;, we can generate a large quantity of (average) reflected waves from different material, such as shown below. This large quantity of data is essential to learn how to &lt;strong&gt;sense materials&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;design materials to control waves&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/reflected_moments.jpg&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/reflected_moments.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average and variation of waves reflected from a variety of complex materials. With only reflected signal (one sensor) we can clearly the affect of the different particulate microstructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
