<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Elastic-Waves | Art L Gower</title>
    <link>https://arturgower.github.io/tags/elastic-waves/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://arturgower.github.io/tags/elastic-waves/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Elastic-Waves</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2026 Artur L Gower</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 17:43:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://arturgower.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Elastic-Waves</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/tags/elastic-waves/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elastic waves in bearing raceways: the forward and inverse problem</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/bearings-inverse/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 17:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/bearings-inverse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Turbines are crucial to our energy infrastructure, and ensuring their bearings function with minimal friction while often supporting heavy loads is vital. Vibrations within a bearing can signal the presence of defects, friction or misalignment. However, current detection methods are neither robust nor easy to automate. We propose a more quantitative approach by modelling the elastic waves within bearing raceways. By approximating the raceway as a hollow cylinder, we derive straightforward 4 × 4 systems for its vibrational modes, enabling both forward and inverse problem-solving. We also demonstrate how to significantly reduce the number of required sensors by using a simple prior: the known number of rollers and their angular speed. We present numerical examples showcasing the full recovery of contact traction between bearings and the raceway, as well as the detection of elastic emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The elastic stored energy of initially strained, or stressed, materials: restrictions and third-order expansions</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/third-order-initial-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 19:51:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/third-order-initial-stress/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Universality of the angled shear wave identity in soft viscous solids</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/universal-angled-shear/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 19:51:12 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/publication/nonlinear-elasticity/universal-angled-shear/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mechanical stress within biological tissue can indicate an anomaly, or can be vital of its function, such as stresses in arteries. Measuring these stresses in tissue is challenging due to the complex, and often unknown, nature of the material properties. Recently, a method called the angled shear wave identity was proposed to predict the stress by measuring the speed of two small amplitude shear waves. The method does not require prior knowledge of the material’s constitutive law, making it ideal for complex biological tissues. We extend this method, and the underlying identity, to include viscous dissipation, which can be significant for biological tissues. To generalise the identity, we consider soft viscoelastic solids described by a generalised Newtonian viscous stress, and account for transverse isotropy, a feature that is common in muscle tissue, for instance. We then derive the dispersion relationship for small-amplitude shear waves superimposed on a large static deformation. Similarly to the elastic case, the identity is recovered when the stress in the material is coaxial with the transverse anisotropy. A key result in this paper is that to predict the stress in a viscous material one would need to measure the wave attenuation as well as the wave speed. The case of viscoelastic materials with memory is also discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elastic &amp; acoustic waves</title>
      <link>https://arturgower.github.io/project/acoustic-elastic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://arturgower.github.io/project/acoustic-elastic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our work covers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elastic waves, including vibration and ultrasonics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Constitutive theory of nonlinear elastic materials, which is mostly applied in soft tissue biomechanics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coupling soft-tissue stress with instability patterns and elastic waves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;linear-elastic-waves&#34;&gt;Linear elastic waves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linear elastic waves cover ultrasonics, and are used to make measurements and assess materials. Work in this includes methods to measure stress through changes in wave-speed with applications in &lt;a href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/angled-ultrasonic-stress/&#34;&gt;steel and hard solids&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/ultrasound-stress/&#34;&gt;medical ultrasound&lt;/a&gt;, and measuring &lt;a href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/publication/elastic-waves/thin-stress-2022/&#34;&gt;extremely thin membranes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another theme is use elastic waves in more complex geometries to measure shape changes as well as sources and stress. Our first paper on the theme &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ultrasonics&#34;&gt;Ultrasonics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultrasonics, and elastic waves, are ideal to monitor and measure materials soft and hard. Elastic waves travel through materials without altering their properties, and are sensitive to changes in mechanical properties. The complexity of elastic waves has benefits and drawbacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Benefits: their complexity makes them versatile, allowing them to travel over great distances as a compact signal, or sweep wide areas quickly along surfaces and interfaces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drawbacks: accurate interpretation of ultrasonic waves requires the use of mathematical models, signal processing techniques, and computer codes, which can be time-consuming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motivations to work on ultrasonics include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Non-destructive testing&lt;/em&gt;. Ultrasonic methods are commonly used in non-destructive testing (NDT) applications, such as inspecting welds, detecting cracks in materials, and evaluating the integrity of structures. Mathematical models can help us develop new NDT methods that are more accurate, efficient, and reliable, by predicting how ultrasonic waves behave in different materials and under different conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medical applications&lt;/em&gt;. A technique called shear wave elastography uses a standard ultrasound machine (with a high frame-rate) to produce and visualise elastic shear waves propagating in soft tissue. We use mathematical models to understand what these shear waves can tell us, and how best to generate these shear waves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below we discuss some examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;point-impact-on-a-surface&#34;&gt;Point impact on a surface&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an anisotropic solid is hit at one point, the solid will react by sending waves out in all directions. Because the solid is anisotropic, these waves travel at different speeds in different directions, which creates unique patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/WaveFront.jpeg&#34; data-caption=&#34;illustrates how to calculate the surface wave front (red), after one second, from the surface wave speed (green). That is, the length of v is equal to the speed of the surface wave travelling in the v direction. The blue shading shows how overlapping plane waves form the wave front.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/WaveFront.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    illustrates how to calculate the surface wave front (red), after one second, from the surface wave speed (green). That is, the length of v is equal to the speed of the surface wave travelling in the v direction. The blue shading shows how overlapping plane waves form the wave front.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;alignright&#34;&gt;
  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/BodyWaveFrontTrack.gif&#34; data-caption=&#34;illustrates how overlapping body waves (blue) creates the resulting wave front (red).&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://arturgower.github.io/img/gifs/BodyWaveFrontTrack.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    illustrates how overlapping body waves (blue) creates the resulting wave front (red).
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The work I have done on plane surface waves can be used to predict the result of these point impacts, among other applications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
